Guide to the DJ Steve Fournier Papers
University of Houston Libraries
DJ Steve Fournier Papers
1986-1994
2013-008
Fournier, Steve
1.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection contains documents, photographs, publications, and memorabilia relating to Steve Fournier and his work as a DJ, Rap Pool of America founder, and hip hop promoter in Houston in the 1980s and 1990s.
Biographical Information:
Steve Fournier moved to Houston as an adolescent in the late 1960s. Fournier began DJing professionally in the late 1970s, quickly becoming a fixture in the Houston night club scene. He DJed at several prominent Houston clubs, including Struts Disco, the Boneshaker, and the Rhinestone Wrangler. An avid rap music fan, Fournier was a driving force behind its increasing presence in the clubs, slipping more and more hip hop into his mixes and hosting live rap contests. Fournier also founded the Rap Pool of America in 1985, which became the largest rap record pool in the country. It began with 30 DJs who paid him a monthly fee in return for the latest hip hop albums, and eventually grew to over 200 members. The Rap Pool of America ended in 1998, but Fournier continued working in the rap industry as a consultant to record companies and major labels until about 2002. Although he is now working in a field completely outside the music industry, Fournier still has a strong interest in hip hop and stays involved through occasional consulting and by speaking at music seminars and conferences.
Sources:
Faniel, Maco L. “Hip-Hop in Houston: The Origin and the Legacy.” The History Press. 2013.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Contracts; Memorabilia; Photographs
Personal Name:
Fournier, Steve
Topical Term:
Disc jockeys -- Texas -- Houston; Hip-hop -- Texas -- Houston; Rap (Music) -- Texas -- Houston; Rap musicians -- Texas -- Houston
Acquisition Information:
Donated by Steve Fournier, September 26, 2013
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Scope and Contents
This collection contains documents, photographs, publications, and memorabilia relating to Steve Fournier and his work as a DJ, Rap Pool of America founder, and hip hop promoter in Houston in the 1980s and 1990s. The collection is divided into five series: Rap Performer Contracts, Rap Pool of America Documents, Photographs, Memorabilia, and Publications. Of particular note is the Rap Performer Contracts series which contains performance contracts for several prominent rappers, including Eazy-E, Sir Mix-A-Lot, N.W.A., Public Enemy, and Ice-T.
Detailed List of Contents
- Rap Performer Contracts
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains contracts in which rappers agree to perform at Houston clubs. They are arranged chronologically.
  - Rap Performer Contracts, June 1988–June 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Eazy-E and N.W.A., June 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - D.L.R., June 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - De La Soul, August 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sir Mix-A-Lot, August 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ice-T, September 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Big Daddy Kane, September 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Stetsasonic, October 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Biz Markie, October 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Public Enemy, December 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Boogie Down Productions, January 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Too Short, June 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Rap Pool of America Documents
  - Rap Pool of America Documents, 1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Rap Pool of America Official Rap Top 30, February 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Rap Pool of America Official Rap Top 50, October 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General information letter for applicants, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photographs
  - Photographs, approximately 1980s, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Steve Fournier photograph, approximately 1980s (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 2nd Tyme Around promotional photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Memorabilia
  This series contains several different types of memorabilia collected by Steve Fournier and is divided into these sub-series: Badges, Concert Tickets, and Business Cards.
  - Badges
    - New Music Seminar badge, July 1987 (Box 2)
    - New Music Seminar badge, July 1988 (Box 2)
    - South by Southwest badge, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Club Infinity badge, April 1991 (Box 2)
    - Club Infinity badge, June 1991 (Box 2)
    - Club Infinity badge, undated (Box 2)
    - South by Southwest badge, March 1988 (Box 2)
  - Concert Tickets
    - Fall Rap Fest, September 26, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Eazy-E and N.W.A., June 16, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Sir Mix-A-Lot and De La Soul, August 18, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Bobby Jimmy & The Critters, October 28, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Da Lench Mob, December 4, 1992 (Box 2)
    - 5th Ward Boyz, October 14, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Business Cards
    - Troy Birklett, Short Stop Records (Box 2)
    - Stephen M. J. Fournier, The Rap Pool of America (Box 2)
    - Greg Head, 97.9 KBXX-FM (Box 2)
    - Luscious Ice, 97.9 KBXX-FM (Box 2)
    - Edward Russell, Rap-A-Lot Records (Box 2)
    - Ousmane Sam, The Source (Box 2)
    - Marshall Williams, 98.5 KHYS-FM (Box 2)
    - Ronald Williams, Cash Money Records (Box 2)
- Publications
  - Publications, January 1991, May 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Houston Chronicle article, “City DJ takes on the music as a mission”, January 20, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - H-Town Rapp Magazine, May 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)